十环的传说已经流传了上千年
The legend of the ten rings has been told for thousands of years.
无论这个故事如何演变
Every generation, the story grows.
它的主人公永远都是同一个人
But at its centre there is always one man.
有人说他的十环是火山口里捡来的
Some say he found the rings in a crater
还有人说是墓穴里盗来的
or stole them from a tomb.
他们给了他神一般的力量
They gave him the strength of a god
也赋予了他长生不老的魔法
and the gift of eternal life.
他本可借着十环之力来惩恶扬善
He could have used them for good.
但他想要的 只有征服
But all he wanted... was power.
他打造了一支十环军团
He called his army The Ten Rings.
千百年来，他们扫荡了世界的每个角落
Over the centuries, they spread into every corner of the world.
他们潜伏于暗中
They moved in the shadows...
颠覆各方政权
Toppled governments...
也改写了历史
And changed the course of history.
凭借着十环之力 他早已称霸千年
He chased money and power for a thousand years.
但他却还不满足
But he still wanted more.
听过塔罗的传说吗
Have you heard the legend of Ta Lo?
一个隐士的村庄 在那里神族的功法代代相传
A hidden village with mythical creatures and ancient magic.
传说中的神兽和古老的法术还都存在
Where people practise a martial arts style from the gods.
我要找到这个地方
I want to find it.
明白 我这就派侦察队去一探究竟
Of course. I'll send a scout to explore the area,
然后有消息立马跟您汇报
and come back with more information.
我们现在就去
I want to go now.
竹林在…正在动
The forest... ...is moving.
这世上再也没有可以让他征服的地方了
He had nothing left on Earth to conquer.
于是他找上了我的家乡
That's when he came for my home.
塔罗的入口在哪
Where's the entrance to Ta Lo?
我们村庄不欢迎你
You're not welcome in our village.
你好像不知道我是谁
You don't know who you're talking to.
我不管你是谁
I don't care who you are.
走吧 不要自找麻烦
Turn around now, and I won't have to hurt you.
就这点本事
Is that all?
那是我第一次见到你的父亲
That was the first time I met your father.
我从没想过自己会为他动心
He was the last person I thought I'd fall for.
但爱总是自有安排
But love had other plans.
尚气 十环的传说啊 讲都讲不完
Shang-Chi, there's much more to know about the legend of the rings,
等你长大了 自然就会了解的
but you'll learn about that when you're older.
可爸爸的十环那么厉害 你是怎么打败他的
If Dad's rings were so powerful, how did you beat him?
妈妈的故乡 塔罗 有一个神龙 他是我们的保护神
Where I'm from, we are empowered
他将魔法赋予在了我们每个人身上
by the magic of the Great Protector.
当你领悟了神龙之心
When you have the heart of our dragon,
你就可以做很多了不起的事情
you can do some amazing things.
那你现在还有魔法吗
Can you still do those things?
妈妈离开的时候啊 把魔法还给了神龙
I left those powers in Ta Lo with our dragon,
但是妈妈得到的更宝贵
but what I got in return is so much better.
这个给你
I want you to have this.
如果有一天你迷路了 它会帮你找到回家的路
Whenever you feel lost, this will help you find your way home.
记住了吗
Can you remember that?
好吧。
Okay.
先生 您好 欢迎光临费尔蒙特……我来开车
Hello, sir, welcome to the Fairmont... I'm driving.
不行 凯蒂
No, you're not... Katy.
嘿 嘿 回来
Hey, hey, get back here.
把钥匙给我
Give me the key.
请开门
Please open the door.
听听这引擎
Oh, my God.
-下车 -你上车
- Get out. - You get in!
听着 要是出了什么问题 我们都得失业
Look, if happens to this thing, we're gonna be jobles
而且下辈子都得还债了
and in debt for the rest of our lives.
拜托 不会有事的
Oh, come on. Nothing's gonna happen to this car.
我是亚洲杰夫·戈登
I'm the Asian Jeff Gordon.
我不认识这个人
I don't know who that is.
全美改装车竞赛历史上获奖最多的人
Most career wins in all of NASCAR history?
请你下车
Please get out of the car.
尚 我们已经是十年老朋友了 好吗
Shaun, we've been friends for 10 years, okay?
你也清楚 我又不笨
You know I'm not an idiot.
上车吧 我会慢慢开的
Please, get in. I'll go slow.
凯蒂 小心…
Katy, watch the...
高中时第一次见到凯蒂 我就知道她是一个惹事精
I knew Katy was trouble the first day we met in high school.
当时我总被人欺负 我们都总会因为各种原因被人欺负
I was getting picked on a lot, for all the reasons we all get picked on a lot.
况且我才到美国 英语也不好 记得有一天我在去吃午饭的路上
Plus, I had just moved to the US, so I was struggling with my English, and I was on my way to lunch
有一个体型比我大一圈的人 在走廊另一头大喊 “哟 江南Style”
one day when this guy who was like twice my size yells at me from down the hall,"What's up, Gangnam Style?"
然后我喊回去“白痴 我不是韩国人”
So I yelled back, "I'm not Korean, idiot."
我站在角落，看到那男的把书包一放 满脸怒气
And I turn the corner, and I see this guy drop his backpack, he's getting all up in his face
准备给我来上一拳 就在这时 凯蒂不知道从哪儿冒出来
And right before he was about to throw the first punch, Katy comes out of nowhere,
站在我们中间 然后开始大喊 加州旅馆的歌词
steps right between us and starts screaming the lyrics to Hotel California.
什么
What?
这就是混淆视听的艺术 对笨蛋非常有效
It's the art of confusion. Works great on stupid people.
我们就是这样认识的
And that's how we met.
然后我把他拉到停车场 凯蒂告诉我
Then I pulled him into the parking lot... At which point she revealed
她把那男的野马车钥匙顺走了
that she had also swiped the keys to the guy's Mustang.
于是 我们就在附近游车河
Yeah, we went on a little joyride around the block.
当时你妻子也在车里
And your wife was in the car, too.
-真的 你当时在 -什么
- That's true. You were. - What?
我只是坐在后排而已
I was just in the back seat.
那也是车的一部分
That's a part of the car.
仍然是坐在车里
That's still a part of the car.
你怎么从没说过这件事
How have you never told me this story?
你知道的 你老婆在做律师之前 可是很狂野的
You know, before she was a lawyer, your girl was pretty wild.
发生什么了
Oh! What happened?
我长大了
I grew up.
这话是什么意思
What's that supposed to mean?
Yeah, what's that supposed to mean?
意思是也许到了某个时刻 你就该停止兜风享乐
That maybe there's a point where you're supposed to stop going on joyrides
并开始思考发挥自己的潜能
and start thinking about living up to your potential.
你是在开玩笑吧 苏
Please tell me you're kidding, Soo.
听着，我们现在生活着的这个世界 一半的人口 随时可能消失
Look, we're now living in a world where at any moment half the population can just disappear.
生命如此短暂 如此脆弱
Life's too short and too fragile.
凯蒂，你是个有伯克利荣誉学位的泊车员 尚恩能说四种语言
Katy, you're a valet driver with an honours degree from Berkeley, and Shaun can speak, like, four languages.
你们是我认识的人里最有才华的
You've always been the most talented people I know.
我只是不明白为什么你们害怕把才华用在正事上
I just don't get why you're scared to actually use it for something serious.
哇哦
Wow.
你说话像我妈 你打扮得…也有点像她
You sound like my mom. You also... dress like her a little bit, too.
你从哪里买的这件衣服 塔尔伯茨(女性服饰品牌)吗
Where's this from, Talbots?
我们才不是在逃避成年呢
We're not running from adulthood.
做自己喜欢的工作怎么就算逃避了
How is it running to have jobs that you actually like?
是啊 这根本说不通
Yeah, that doesn't even make any sense.
难道代客泊车很容易吗
Did you think valet parking is easy?
这大概是史上最具挑战性的工作了
It's like the most challenging job ever.
你得有人际交往能力 驾驶技术 苏连侧方位停车都不会呢
You need people skills, driving skills... Soo can't even parallel park.
下载都快十二点了 我们还要上早班呢
Well, it's almost midnight. We got the early shift.
我们应该负起责任来 该睡觉了
Should probably be responsible, go to sleep.
是啊 我们应该负起责任来 该睡觉了
Yeah, we can be responsible. We can do that.
或者... 由一场魔毯之旅 看尽路旁与地下的奇景
Or... Over, sideways and under on a...
骑着我的马 走上老城路
Take my horse to the old town road
我会闭上双眼 我不想
I'm gonna Close my eyes I don't wanna...
早上好 陈太太
Morning, Mrs Chen.
她还没好呢
She's not ready yet.
先进来吃点粥等等吧
Come have some joe while you wait.
凯蒂 尚恩来啦
Katy, Shaun's here.
好啦 妈 我一会就来
Yeah, Mom, be there in a minute.
瑞华 你怎么还没去帮你爸给店里进货
Ruihua, you're supposed to be helping your dad stock the shop.
妈妈 我饿着肚子怎么干活 一会儿腿该抽筋了
Mom, I can't work on an empty stomach, my legs get crampy.
怎么不叫尚恩去 他天天都来这里蹭饭吃
Maybe Shaun can help him instead of just showing up every day to eat our food.
我很乐意帮忙
I'm happy to help.
不用 瑞华该干的活儿 让他自个儿去
No, it's Ruihua's job, let him do it.
外婆
Waipo.
这是外公的座位
That seat's for Waigong.
对不起
Oh, sorry.
今年清明节 我准备给他 他最喜欢的东西
He's getting all his favourite things this year for the Day of the Dead.
你确定外公能在下面享用这些洋葱圈和香烟吗
Are you sure that Waigong's allowed to take Funyuns and cigarettes back to the afterlife?
他什么都可以吃
He can take anything.
去年我在他的坟前放了一瓶白酒 第二天没啦
Last year I put a bottle of whisky on his grave... And it was gone the next morning.
我知道你们觉得我很傻
I know you kids think it's silly.
我们没觉得您傻 外婆
We don't think it's silly, Waipo.
只是知道外公他在天之灵 肯定也希望您走出悲伤 享受生活
We just know Waigong would've wanted you to move on and enjoy your life.
“走出悲伤”是美国人的观念
"Moving on" is an American idea.
你可是个美国妈妈 别忘了
You're American, Mom! Don't forget.
尚恩 我女儿这周有没有“跳槽”的打算呀
Shaun, did my daughter apply to any new jobs this week?
她很喜欢现在这份工作
She really likes her job.
我俩都是
We both do.
嗯哼
Mm-hmm.
当初外公从湖南大老远过来
Waigong didn't move here from Hunan
可不是为了让你在这儿给人泊车讨生活的
so you could park cars for a living.
这话倒提醒了我 咱们再不走就赶不上公交了
Well, on that note, I think we're gonna miss our bus.
对不起 我找了份不体面的工作
I'm sorry for my unacceptable job.
昨晚还熬夜通宵 享受人生
And for staying out late last night, trying to enjoy my life.
但总有一天 你会为我感到骄傲的 我保证
But one day, I'll make you proud, I promise.
我为你骄傲 姐
I'm proud of you, sis.
泊车 超难的
Parking cars is super hard.
谢了老弟
Thanks, bro.
等你考到了驾照 就能跟我一样实现梦想了
Maybe one day you'll pass your driver's test, live the dream like me.
-尚恩 我们走吧 -走了 外婆
Come on, Shaun, let's go.
你们什么时候结婚
When are you two going to get married?
外婆 我们只是朋友
Waipo, we're just friends.
好吧 走走走
All right. Go, go, go.
瞧瞧那个女生
Look. Look at that. Look at that girl.
她居然在公交车上写论文
She's writing a research paper on a bus.
所以呢
So?
我妈一度幻想从她的阴道里能爬出来这种完美女儿
That is exactly the daughter my mom wishes came out of her vagina.
对不起 她人就是这样
I'm sorry about her.
怎么了
How's it goin'?
项链给我 就没有人会受伤
Give me the pendant, and no one gets hurt.
你认识这家伙？
Do you know this guy?
我听不懂你在说啥 哥们
I don't know what you're talking about, dude.
-嘿 怎么回事 离我远点 -唔喔
- Hey! Get off of me! - Whoa.
你们他妈的有什么毛病？
What is wrong with you, asshole?
我不想惹麻烦
I don't want any trouble.
那就把项链交出来
Then give us the pendant!
你找错人了
You have the wrong guy!
他看起来很能打吗
Does he look like he can fight?
别闹了 大哥
Come on, bro!
你还好吧
You okay?
大家好 这里是克里夫 在公交车上为您实时直播
Yo, what up, y'all? It's your boy Klev, comin' at you live on the bus.
我年轻的时候练过一点武术
I actually did take a little bit of martial arts as a youth
所以我现在试试解说一下这场打斗
so I'm gonna try and grade this fight as we're goin'.
我靠
Holy shit.
你是谁?
Who are you?
兄弟 你可以的
You got this, bro!
额 当我没说
My bad.
不 不 不!
No, no, no!
对不起
Sorry.
这他妈到底什么情况
What the hell's going on?
你非得现在问吗
You really wanna talk about this now?
司机不行了
Bus driver is down.
我不会去接盘的
I'm not gonna handle this.
我一开车就被人骂
Every time I've tried to drive a bus, I get yelled at.
滚开 傻逼
Go, you freak!
快开门啊
Open the door, please!
后面那节车厢快掉了
The back is about to go.
等我信号 你就向右急转
On my signal, make a hard right.
啥信号？
What signal?
所有人快去前车厢
Everybody to the front now!
走走走走
Go! Go, go, go.
你好啊 你好啊 你也好啊
What's up, y'all? What's up, y'all? What's up, y'all?
你和你妹妹罪有应得
You and your sister deserve what's coming.
大家扶稳了
Hold on, everybody!
我的天
Oh, God.
救命
Oh, my God!
抱歉
Sorry. Heh.
合作愉快
We make a good team.
尚恩 喂
Shaun. Hey.
告诉我刚才到底什么情况
You need to tell me what the hell's going on.
你在干嘛 你要去哪
What are you doing? Where are you going?
-澳门 -澳门？
- Macau. - Macau?
那些家伙要去找我妹妹 我要在他们之前找到她
Those guys are going after my sister next, and I have to get to her first.
你还有个妹妹?
You have a sister?
我知道你现在很懵
Look, I know this is confusing.
我保证 回来之后会跟你解释的
I'll explain it when I get back, I promise.
不 不
No, no.
得了吧
Hell no, dude.
别给我在这扯蛋
This is bullshit!
我认识你小半辈子了
I have been by your side for half your life.
我明白有些事你不想说 我也从来不会去问
I get there are things you never wanted to talk about, and I never wanted to push.
但是刚才一个胳膊上装着大砍刀的男的
But a guy with a freaking machete for an arm
把我们坐的巴士砍成了两半 尚恩
just chopped our bus in half, Shaun!
你到底是什么来头？
Who the hell are you?
我妹妹几个月前寄了这个给我
My sister sent me this a few months ago.
这上面的地址应该就是她住的地方
I think it's the address of where she's staying.
刚才那些家伙 是我爸爸派来的
Those guys back there were sent by my dad.
什么?
What?
要是他们再去伤害她…
If they hurt her...
抱歉，我得走了
I'm sorry, but I have to go.
好吧
Fine.
你可以在飞机上跟我解释
You can explain on the plane.
什么 不 凯蒂你别… 你可以在飞机上跟我解释清楚 尚恩
What? No, Katy, you can't just... You can explain on the plane, Shaun!
妈妈去世后 我爸爸就开始训练我
After my mom died... my dad started my training.
日复一日 日出到日落 我学尽各种杀人的办法
From sunup to sundown, I was taught every possible way to kill a man.
14岁时 我已经记不清了 妈妈还在时的生活是什么样了
By the time I was 14, I could barely remember what life was like before she died.
也就是那一年 他派我去执行了第一个任务
That's how old I was when he sent me on my first assignment.
我愿意为他做任何事
I was willing to do anything he wanted.
就算他叫我把这个世界焚烧殆尽
If he asked me to burn the world down,
我也… 牛肉还是素食？
I would've asked him... Beef or vegetarian?
我们的鸡肉餐发完了 所以只剩牛肉或者素食了
We're all out of the chicken, so I can only offer you beef or vegetarian?
唔…-素食吧 -我也一样
Um... - Vegetarian would be great. - Yeah, same.
-好的 -谢谢
- Okay. - Thank you.
所以…我们素食也没有了
So... Oh, we're out of the vegetarian too.
现在只有牛肉了
Now we only have beef.
那就牛肉 我们也没得选了不是吗
Beef. 'Cause that's all you have, right?
-好的 你要牛肉… -嗯
- Okay, you'll have the beef. - Yes.
-那么… -牛肉
- And... - Beef.
-我也要牛肉 -好的两份牛肉
- And the beef. - Two beefs.
你都挺过来了吗？
Did you go through with it?
我觉得不能再回他身边了 所以我只能…逃跑
I knew that I couldn't go back to him, so I just... ran.
我知道这些对你来说很难消化
I know this is a lot to dump on you.
你妈妈的事我很遗憾
I'm sorry about your mom.
还有一件事要告诉你 其实我的本命不是尚恩
I should also probably mention that my name's not technically Shaun.
什么
What?
那你的名字是什么
What is it?
尚气
It's Shang-Chi.
双气
Shaun-Chi.
不 尚气
No. Shang-Chi.
爽气
Shaun-Chi.
商
Shang.
-尚恩 -尚
- Shaun. - Shang.
擅
Shan.
Shi-ang-尚
S-H-A-N-G. Shang.
尚？
Shang?
对
Yeah.
你把尚改成了尚恩
You changed your name from Shang to Shaun?
对 我不…
Yeah, I don't... Yeah.
怪不得你爸能找到你
I wonder how your father found you.
我改名的时候才15岁 好吗
Okay, I was 15 years old. All right?
你是怎么想的？
What is your name change logic?
你打算隐姓埋名
You're going into hiding.
-昂 -然后把自己的名字迈克尔 改成了迈歇尔
- Okay. - And your name is Michael, you go on and change it to Mishael.
不 不是这么回事儿
That's not what happened.
就好像 嗨 我叫吉娜
It's like, "Hi, my name's Gina.
我要隐姓埋名了 我的新名字是洁娜
"I'm gonna go into hiding. My new name's Gina."
听不见了 不好意思
Can't hear you. I'm sorry.
哈 你听不到才怪
Yeah, okay. Oh, yeah, you can hear me.
在这签名才能进去
Sign here to get in.
我在找我的妹妹 徐夏灵
I'm looking for my sister, Xu Xialing.
听说过她吗
Have you heard of her?
这是是她给我的地址
This is the address she gave me.
好的吧
Okay.
她看起来人挺好的
Seems like a nice fella.
这架电梯也肯定符合安全规范
And this elevator is definitely up to code.
绝对不会一下子掉到楼底 或者…
There's absolutely no chance of it just falling off the side of the building...
公车男孩
Bus Boy!
我靠 你三天就两百万播放量
Uh... Two million views in three days, bro!
靠 老铁
Damn, dude.
不妙
Oh, no.
哇 司机也来了 你的车技实在是太帅了
And you're the driver!
我中文不好
Oh, my Chinese sucks.
没事
Oh, all good.
-我能说点英文 -那太好了
- I speak A-B-C. - Oh, great.
-我是庄庄 -庄庄
- I'm Jon Jon. - Jon Jon.
欢迎来到金匕首俱乐部
Welcome to the Golden Daggers Club.
好 我带你去做热身
Okay, let's get you ready to fight.
等等 什么
Wait. What?
我们是全球多平台运营
We're a multi-platform global operation.
每场打斗都在暗网上直播
Every fight livestreamed on the dark web.
我们说话的这会功夫 成千上万的观众在下注
Thousands of viewers placing bets as we speak.
我们会带你走上人生巅峰
This is gonna take your brand to a whole new level.
我有点糊涂了
Think there's been some sort of confusion.
我喜欢他们的钉子脸
I like your spike face.
谢了
Thanks!
按理来说 你得一路打到中心擂台 但像你这样的格斗明星
Usually, you gotta fight your way to centre ring, but a viral star like you?
你可以破例晋级 宝贝
Front of line, baby.
我不是来打架的
I'm not here to fight anybody. Okay?
我来找我妹妹的 徐夏灵
I'm looking for my sister, Xu Xialing.
没听说过
Never heard of her.
我们刚失去了一位选手 所以下一个你上场
We just lost a fighter at the last minute, so you get the next slot.
打得不错 海伦
Nice one, Helen.
他真的要和这些人打架吗
Is he gonna be fighting in one of these?
不不不 这些都是最低级的比赛
Oh, no, no, no. These are like low-level fights.
你要打的人 在上面
You're gonna be fighting up there.
很痛诶 利奥
That hurt, Emil.
想尝尝有多痛吗
You want me to show you how it feels?
王！王！王！
Wong! Wong! Wong!
干得漂亮 王
Go, Wong!
我永远都押亚洲人赢
I always bet on Asian.
我的天哪
Oh, my God.
好吧 我不会到擂台上去的 好吗
Yeah, look, I'm not going up there, okay?
-我只是想来… -唔喔 唔喔 唔喔
- I'm just trying to... - Whoa, whoa, whoa.
现在后悔太晚了
It's too late to back out now.
-你已经同意了 兄弟 -什么？
- You already committed, bro. - What?
-你签了合同 记得吗
You signed the contract, remember?
你的名字在花名册上
Your name's on the roster.
赌局已经悄然开始了
The bets are piling in.
-真的吗 我们能分多少钱 -超多
- Really? What's our cut? - Oh, it's huge.
没所谓的好吗
It doesn't matter.
非常有所谓
It matters.
老兄 我看到你和五个杀手 其中还有一个胳膊装砍刀
Dude, I saw you fight five assassins and a giant
的罗马尼亚巨人 在行驶的车上搏斗
Romanian with a razor for an arm on a moving bus.
现在只要打一个人就行了
This is just one guy.
上吧 这样我们都能拿到钱
Just do it. Then we all get paid,
然后我来帮你找你要找的人
and then I'll help you find whoever you're looking for.
上 你能行的
Come on. You got this.
-你可以的 -别紧张
- You got this. - Don't be nervous.
谢谢你！
Thank you.
-客气 -客气
- Yeah. - Yeah.
你的下巴还好吗
How's the jaw?
你得像练习的时候那样 控制出拳
Maybe you'll start controlling those punches like we practised?
那个人真不错
Love that guy.
现在 把衣服脱了
Now take your shirt off.
女士们 先生们 我们期待已久的对决即将开始
Ladies and gentlemen, the fight we've all been waiting for.
轰动全网的 从美国旧金山远道而来的
The incredible viral sensation, all the way from San Francisco, USA,
公车男孩！
it's Bus Boy!
你衣服呢
What happened to your shirt?
而他今晚的对手
And his opponent for tonight,
正是我们澳门令人闻风丧胆的杀手
it's Macau's own fearsome killer...
徐夏灵！
Xu Xialing!
妹妹
Sister.
等等 等一下
Wait, wait!
你怎么了你
What are you doing?
我知道你在生我的气
I know you're upset.
但是我有急事跟你…
But can you hear me out?
没有时间打了
We don't have time for this.
喔 肯定很疼
Ooh, that's gotta hurt.
你能不能不打我
Can you please stop hitting me?
住手! 我是来帮你的
Stop it! I'm trying to help you!
爸要来找你
Dad's coming for you.
我不会再跟你打了
I'm not fighting you.
你不应该回来的
You shouldn't have come back.
有的时候 我在练功 我闭上我的眼睛
Sometimes when I'm doing my forms... I close my eyes,
就可以感觉 她就在我身后
and it's like I can feel her.
你有这个感觉吗
Do you ever feel like that?
没有
No.
我知道你为什么要去那儿
I know what you're going there to do.
我不知道他跟你说了什么 但是妈妈… 妈妈已经死了
I don't know what he's telling you, but Mom... Mom's dead.
不要把我扔在这
Please don't leave me here.
灵灵 我三天以后就回来
I'll be back in three days.
徐夏灵 太精彩了
Xu Xialing, you're amazing!
我们爱你 徐夏灵
We love you, Xu Xialing! Whoo!
这地方归你管？
You run this place?
这地方归我管
I own it.
你这些钱是哪里来的
Where'd you get all that money?
你押我输？
Did you bet against me?
没有啊
No.
嗨 夏灵 我是凯蒂
Hi, Xialing. I'm Katy.
你真是酷毙了
You're, like, such a badass.
每个动作都堪称经典
Everything that you do is, like, so cool.
太酷了
That was really cool.
你的裤子很好看
I like your pants.
谢谢 谢谢
Thank you. Thanks. Yeah.
你来干什么
What do you want?
十环在旧金山伏击了我们
The Ten Rings ambushed us in San Francisco.
我看到视频了
I saw the video.
他们拿走了我的项链
They took my pendant.
他们的下一个目标就是你
They're gonna come for yours next.
我摸不准他现在到底想干嘛
I don't know what he wants with them,
但肯定不是什么好事
but we both know it can't be good.
你知道他临走前跟我说什么吗
You know what he said to me when he left?
“三天后我就会回来”
"I'll be back in three days."
三天后 我去妈妈的祠堂等他
And after three days, I went to our mom's shrine and waited.
三天变成一周
Three days turned into a week,
一周变成一个月 一个月变成六年
a week turned to a month, and a month turned to six years.
我才渐渐意识到 我不再需要他了
That's how long it took me to realise I didn't need him any more.
我凭一己之力打造了这个地方
I built this place on my own.
那个时候不需要你 现在就更不需要了
I didn't need you then, and I don't need you now.
那你为什么给我寄那张明信片
Then why would you send me the postcard?
什么明信片
What postcard?
这个不是我寄的
I didn't send you this.
这里有后门吗
Is there a back exit?
尚恩
Shaun.
嘿  嘿！嘿 开门
Hey. Hey! Hey, open up!
她已经跑了 兄弟
She's gone, dude.
我们该怎么办
What do we do?
我们该怎么办?
嗯…
Uh...
快点
Come on!
不会吧 去你的 我绝不会干这档事的
Oh, hell no. Screw you! I'm not doing this.
如果我们能到电梯那 就能接着跳进下一层
If we make it to the elevator, we can hop in on the next floor.
没有别的办法了 凯蒂 现在就得下去
Katy, we're out of options. We have to go now.
一 二 三！
One, two, three.
唔喔
Whoa.
往电梯跑 别回头
Just head straight for that elevator.
你可以的
You got this.
我给你争取点时间 你继续走
I'll buy you some time. Just keep going.
♪夜色下的沙漠公路上 寒风拂过我的发梢♪
On a dark desert highway Cool wind in my hair
尚恩！
Shaun!
尚恩！ 尚恩！
Shaun! Shaun!
我的天
Oh, my God! Ohhh!
我来了!
I'm coming!
尚恩
Shaun!
坚持住
Hang on.
拉住你了
Gotcha.
尚恩
Shaun!
凯蒂!
Katy!
把我丢在这 说走就走
You left us for dead!
现在你知道什么滋味儿了
Now you know how it feels.
他要这个项链做什么
What does he want with the pendant...
在美国呆了几年 胆儿也变小了？
Did America make you soft?
项链在她手上
He has the pendant!
我跟我手下说过 你要是动起真格来就杀不了你 他们不信
I told my men they wouldn't be able to kill you if they tried.
还好我是对的
Glad I was right.
我太想你了
I've missed you, my son.
我们回家吧
Let's go home.
我的儿子回家了
My son is home.
把姑娘们带去她们的房间
Take the girls to their room.
我这周经历了许多心惊胆战的事
I've seen some really scary stuff this week,
但跟你爸相比 真是小巫见大巫
but your dad's on, like, a whole 'nother level.
他会杀了我们吗
Is he gonna kill us?
只要言听计从 不多说话 他会忘记你的存在
Just nod. Don't talk. He'll forget you're there.
这边是我的生存之道
That's how I survived.
他一直都这么对你吗？
He always treat you like that?
从我母亲去世之后开始
Only after my mom died.
他说他不敢看我
He said he couldn't look at me
因为看着我总会想起母亲
because I reminded him of her.
他不允许我和男孩子一起训练
I wasn't allowed to train with the boys.
但我看过他们所有的训练内容
But I watched everything they did
我要求自己做的比他们更好
and taught myself to do it better.
那你什么时候离开的?
When did you leave?
我16岁的时候逃离了这里
I ran away when I was 16.
当我知道我哥不会再回来的时候
As soon as I knew my brother wasn't coming back.
所以你16岁的时候
You started an underground fight ring in Macau
就在澳门开了家地下竞技场？
when you were 16 years old?
如果父亲不让我染指他的帝国
If my dad won't let me into his empire,
我就建一个自己的帝国
I'm gonna build my own.
你太牛了
Hell yeah.
尚气
Shang-Chi.
可以了
That's enough.
你最近有在练习英语吗
Have you been practicing your English?
练了
Yes.
你一定要在强健身体的同时磨炼自己的心智
You have to strengthen your mind along with your body.
如果你想拥有它们
If you want them to be yours one day,
就必须向我证明你足够强大
you have to show me you're strong enough to carry them.
你是怎么找到我的?
How did you find me?
我一直 知道我的孩子在哪里
I always know where my children are.
我给了你十年的时间让你去过自己的生活 你收获了什么呢
I gave you 10 years to live your life, and where did it get you?
是时候回到我身边了
Now it's time for you to take your place by my side.
不可能
That's not gonna happen.
美国妞
American girl.
她叫凯蒂
Her name is Katy.
那你的中文名字叫什么?
What is your Chinese name?
瑞文
Ruiwen.
名字是很神圣的 瑞文
Names are sacred, Ruiwen.
它联结的不仅是我们自身 还有我们的先人
They connect us not only to ourselves, but to everyone who came before.
有个很有趣的故事
A funny story.
几年前 一个美国的恐怖分子
Some years ago, a terrorist from America
需要一个坏蛋 来摧毁你们的国家
needed a boogeyman to bring your country to its knees.
所以他盗用了十环这个名字
So, he appropriated The Ten Rings.
我的十环
My Ten Rings.
但是他不知道我的真名 就自己起了一个
But because he didn't know my actual name, he invented a new one.
你们知道他最后起了个什么名字吗
Do you know the name he chose?
满大人(有“柑橘”义)
The Mandarin.
他给他的名号起了个水果名
He gave his figurehead the name of a chicken dish.
居然还很管用
And it worked.
整个美国都陷入了恐慌
America was terrified.
只是因为一个“橘子”
Of an orange.
其实我这一生 有过很多名字
The truth is, I've had many names throughout my life.
战王 坎大师 地球上最危险的人
The Warrior King, Master Khan, the most dangerous man on Earth.
有很长一段时间 我以为这就是我人生的意义
For years, I thought that was all I was meant to be.
但自从我遇到了他们的妈妈以后 一切都变了
But when I met their mother, everything changed.
她让我发现了新的自己
She showed me a part of myself I didn't know was there.
让我重新认识了这个世界
It was like I was seeing the world for the first time.
为了和我在一起 她抛下了一切
She gave up everything so we could be together.
而我也是一样
And so did I.
这是谁呀
You know who's in there?
我说 你好 妹妹
Say, "Hello, little sister!"
过了这么多年 我终于找到了 值得我为其变老的东西
After all those years, I finally found something worth growing old for.
我的真名叫文武
My real name is Wenwu.
她是唯一一个这么叫我的人
She was the only one who called me that.
在她离世以后
And when she died...
我迷失了很久
I was lost for many years.
但现在不会了
But I'm not lost any more.
当你们两个离家出走
When you children ran away,
我迫切需要你们母亲灵魂的指引
I was so desperate to connect with your mother,
我全身心地投入到对她家乡的研究中
I threw myself back into the studies of her village.
传说中的塔罗
The legendary Ta Lo.
我没能找到通往村子入口的秘密路线
I wasn't able to find the secret path to the village entrance,
但我发现了他们一直在隐藏的东西
but I did find what they are hiding.
在那座大山的深处有一道门
There's a gate deep in their mountains.
你们的母亲就在那里等着我们
Your mother is waiting for us there.
我知道这很难接受
I know this is a lot.
如果不是她亲口告诉我 我也不敢相信
I might not have believed it if she didn't tell me herself.
你在说什么啊
What are you talking about?
当时我就坐在这张椅子上 全神贯注地做着研究
I was sitting right here in this seat, deep in my research...
然后她和我说话了
and she spoke to me.
就好像她真的在这个房间里一样
It was like she was standing in this room.
我能感受到她的呼吸拂过我的脸颊 手掌抚在我的背上
I could feel her breath on my cheek and her hand on my back.
她告诉我 她需要我的帮助
She told me she needs my help.
怎么帮
To do what?
从她族人的手中救出她
To save her from her people.
我们坠入爱河后 你母亲希望我们定居塔罗
After we fell in love, your mother wanted us to live in Ta Lo.
她请求长老们的允准 长老们却拒绝了
She asked permission from the elders, and they refused.
他们说我不配
They said I wasn't worthy.
如果没有被拒绝
She would still be with us.
她就不会死 我们就会一起在那里生活
We would all be living there together.
是塔罗害了我们
Ta Lo did this to us.
他们把她关在那扇门后面 以示惩罚
They locked her behind that gate to punish her.
你还没看出来吗
Don't you see?
她给我们留下了线索
She's leaving clues for us.
她希望我们找到她 带她回家 一家团圆
She wants us to find her and bring her home, so we can be a family again.
爸 妈已经走了
Dad, Mom's gone.
她并没有在大门后和你对话 她也没有给我们留下任何线索
She's not talking to you from behind a gate, and she's not leaving any clues for us.
那这些是什么
Then what are these?
去塔罗的通道被移动的迷宫守卫着
The passage to Ta Lo is guarded by a moving maze.
但是森林中有一条直达的路径
But there's a direct path through the forest
一年仅开放一次 在清明节的时候
that only opens once a year on Qingming Jie.
要想通过 只有知道路线和开放的具体时间
To get through, you need to know the route and the exact time it opens.
现在我都知道了
Now I know both.
三天之后 我们会救出我的夫人 带她回家
Three days from now, we will rescue my wife from her prison and bring her home.
这就是你来这里的理由
This is why you're here.
帮我把她带回我们身边
To help me bring her back to us.
如果他们不让你打开大门怎么办
And what happens if they don't let you open the gate?
那我们就把村子夷为平地
We'll burn the village to the ground.
什么
What?
你不能就这样带兵攻打母亲的村庄 这太疯狂了
You can't just march into our mom's village with this bullshit.
你知不知道这有多疯狂…
I mean, do you have any idea how insane...
嘿
Hey!
你们要带我去哪儿
Where are you taking me?
你还要装多久
When will you stop pretending?
把他们关起来
Lock them up.
没关系
It's okay, my dear.
咱们一家人很快就能在一起了
We're all going to be together soon.
所以说 咱就是说 有点迷惑了
So, um, pretty confused right now,
因为我一开始觉得 你爸有妄想症必须去看心理医生
because, uh, initially I thought your dad should definitely see a therapist for his delusions,
但之后那个龙头 像施了法一样 喷出来一副水做的地图
but then that dragon vomited a magical water map,
所以我现在都不知道什么才是真的了
and now I have no idea what's real.
关于你母亲家乡的那些话是真的吗
Is what he said about your mom's village true?
我们小的时候 他曾经讲过塔罗的故事
She used to tell us stories about Ta Lo when we were kids.
那是处于另一个空间的村庄 到处都是奇幻生物
A village in another dimension full of magical creatures.
我之前只当作神话故事
I thought it was just a fairy tale.
但如果爸说的是真的呢
What if Dad's right?
你是说如果妈真的被自己的族人关起来了？
About Mom being locked behind a gate by her own people?
比这更疯狂的事情都已经发生了
Crazier things have turned out to be true.
听我说 我不知道这一切都他妈是怎么回事
Look, I don't know what the hell is going on,
但如果我们不杀出去并在他之前找到塔罗
but if we don't find a way to get to Ta Lo before him,
他会把咱们家仅剩的都毁掉
he's gonna destroy everything that's left of our family.
这个家很久之前就已经被毁了
This family was destroyed a long time ago.
什么鬼
The hell was that?
喔
Oh.
你们真的要朝那个声音的方向去？
You're going toward that noise?
麦克白 敲醒邓肯吧
"Wake Duncan with thy knocking.
但愿你能够如此
"Oh, I would'st though could'st.
不想我所为 我最好忘掉（自己）
"My deed 'twere best not..."
你们好啊 小可爱们
Oh, hello, loves.
现在是哪一年了？
What year is it?
你是谁
Who are you?
特雷弗 ？斯莱特里？
Trevor? Slattery?
来自利物浦的演员?
The actor from Liverpool?
等等
Wait.
你们是那位掌权者的孩子？
Are you the governor's kids?
我一直在准备一个独白话剧 等到你们的接风宴表演
I've been preparing a monologue for your homecoming dinner.
她要去哪
Oh. Where's she going?
你为什么在这下面?
Why are you down here?
是这样 很久以前 我接到一个恐怖分子的角色
Well, some time ago, I was offered the role of a terrorist.
我知道 这个剧情老套又无聊 我也举这么觉得
I know, facile, trite, I couldn't agree more.
但机不可失 失不再来 你知道吗
But times were lean, you know what I mean?
总之就是 制作人说他是BBC的
Anyway, the producer told me he worked for the BBC.
但是 讽刺的转折来了 结果他真的是个恐怖分子
But, ironic twist, it turns out he, in fact, was a terrorist,
我当时根本不是在扮演一个角色
and I wasn't playing a character at all,
我知道 你会觉得我在说你爸坏话
but what I now recognise to be a rather unflattering portrait of your father.
我们都罪有应得
We all got our just deserts.
那个制片人被钢铁侠炸飞了
The producer got blown up by Iron Man,
我也在联邦监狱服了刑
and I served time in federal prison,
不过对我来说反而是个好事
which turned out to be the best thing for me.
我戒了毒，重拾了我热爱的表演
I got clean, I rediscovered my passion.
-然后我爸把你救出来了？ -没错
- Then my dad broke you out? - Exactly.
-为了杀你 -没错
- To kill you. - Exactly.
但是 在他的手下即将把我绑起来处死时
But just as his men were tying me up for my execution,
我表演了一段“麦克白”
I launched into a performance of my Macbeth.
“哪来的敲门声？敲醒邓肯吧！”“但愿你能够如此”
"Whence is that knocking? Wake Duncan "with thy knocking. I would'st though could'st..."
他们简直百看不厌
They couldn't get enough of it.
从那以后 我就一直在为他们表演
I've been doing weekly gigs for the lads ever since.
所以你是他的小丑?
So you're like his jester?
你想看的话 我给你模仿一下
I can give you a quick preview if you like.
“叔叔 叔叔 叔叔…”
"Nuncle, nuncle, nuncle..."
谢谢你 特雷弗 我觉得可以了
Uh, thank you, Trevor. I think we're okay.
现在我们只想找到出去的路
Right now, we really just need to find a way to... What the hell?
什么情况
What the... Oh!
-唔喔 -那是个什么玩意？
- Whoa! - What is that?
那是个什么玩意儿？
What's what?
-那个 那是个什么玩意？ -那个！那个！那个！
- That! What is that? - That! That! That!
你们能看到莫里斯？
You can see Morris?
莫里斯?
Morris?
哦,莫里斯!
Oh, Morris!
他们看得到你！你是真实存在的！
They can see you! You're real!
这么长时间以来 我以为他是我臆想出来的
All this time I thought I was hallucinating him.
真是太好了
Oh, this is such fab news.
他的脸在哪里?
Where's his face?
他对这个话题有点敏感
He's a bit sensitive about that.
哦 是么？
Oh. Really?
莫里斯说他知道你是谁
Morris says he knows who you are.
它…它会跟你说话？
It talks... It talks to you?
如果不是它和我说话 我早就疯了
If he didn't talk to me, I'd have gone mad yonks ago.
他怎么会认识我？
How would he know me?
他说 在塔罗的时候 他和你母亲一起长大
He says he grew up with your mum. In Ta Lo.
你爸爸寻找入口的时候
Apparently, your father picked him up in some magic forest
在奇幻森林里捡到了他
on one of his expeditions to find the entrance.
他希望你能带他回家
He wants you to take him home.
相信我 朋友 如果我知道该怎么做 我一定会的
Believe me, buddy, I would if I knew how.
我爸说 这条路一年只打开一次
According to my dad, the path there only opens once a year.
哦
Oh.
莫里斯说他现在就可以带你去
Morris says he can guide you there right now.
不用等那条路打开 他就能带你穿过迷宫
You can get through the maze without waiting for the path to open.
但是 有一个很大的“但是”
But, and it's a big "but,"
此行非常危险
it's very dangerous.
有多危险
How dangerous?
没有人能活着从那里面出来
No one's ever made it out alive.
但莫里斯有百分之九十确定 他能够带我们安全地通过
But Morris is 90% confident he can guide us through safely.
哦
Oh.
百分之十九
19%.
我做过比这更蠢 风险更高的事情
Look, I've done dumber things with worse odds.
但是即使那个长得像鸡的猪说的是真的…
But even if that chicken-pig is right...
我们仍然困在这里…
we're still locked in your...
唷!
Whew!
你是怎么……爸爸在整个院子下面造了隧道系统
How did you... Dad has a tunnel system under the whole compound.
我上一次就是这么逃跑的
That's how I escaped last time.
哦。
Oh.
这里直接通向车库
This will take us straight to the garage.
哦我的天
Oh, my God.
这车真不错
I kinda like this guy.
下斜坡 直走到大门
Just head up that ramp and through the front gate.
直接就到了
Should be a straight shot.
我们大概有30秒的时间…介意我坐前排吗?
Figure we got about 30 seconds until he... Do you mind?
我坐后排会有点晕车
I get sick in the back. Carsick.
那是我的车啊
That's my car!
该死
God damn it.
抓紧了
Hold on.
还有别的出口吗?
Is there another exit?
在车库的另一头
The other end of the garage.
但是是指纹解锁开门的
But we need a fingerprint to open it.
小心
Incoming!
靠
Shit!
后面怎么样
What's happening back there?
我在尽力
Doing my best.
请扫描掌纹解锁开门
Scan hand print for gate access.
-快点！ -我正在试！
- Hurry up! - I'm trying!
请扫描掌纹解锁开门
Scan hand print for gate access.
尚恩
Shaun!
已解锁
Access approved.
只要我带她回家 他们肯定会回来
They will come back once I bring her home.
准备人手 随时应战
Prepare the men for war.
是 长官
Yes, sir.
我第一次看到纯粹的艺术
The first time I witnessed pure artistry.
是在1968年看《人猿星球》的时候
1968. Planet of the Apes.
我和母亲坐在电影院里 聚精会神地观看那部杰作
I was sitting in the cinema next to my mum, watching mastery unfold before my very eyes.
看完之后 我问她 他们是怎么让猴子做那些事的
After the film, I asked her, "How did they get those monkeys to do those things?"
她拍了拍我的头说“那都是假的 只是表演而已”
And she patted me on the head and she said, "It's not real, pet. It's just acting."
从那时候起 我就觉得
That's when I knew.
如果他们可以教那些猴子 表演得出神入化
If they can teach those monkeys to act that brilliantly,
这么想想 我可以为这个世界带来什么
just imagine what I could bring to the world.
所以你成为了一名演员 因为你以为那些猴子是真的
So you became an actor because you thought the monkeys were actually...
我以为他们真的在骑马 是的
Riding horses? I did. Yes.
但实际上 它们只是在表演而已
When, in fact, they were simply acting
演得好像真的在骑马一样
as if they were riding horses.
不过说实话 我到现在都没整明白是怎么做到的
I still can't get my head round it, to be honest.
真有你的 兄弟
Good for you, dude.
你找到了你的热爱所在 为它付出
You found your passion and went for it,
并凭一己之力削弱了美国政府 但不管怎样
and eventually used it to cripple the US government, but whatever.
啊 是的 谢谢啊
Yeah. No, yeah, thanks.
真不错 但我们还要在这里坐多久
Um, this is really cool and all, but how long do we have to sit here?
莫里斯说的非常清楚
Morris is very clear.
万事俱备 只欠东风
The way through is all about timing.
好吧 但我们还要在这聊多久
Okay, but how long are we talking?
几个小时 还是几天?
Like, hours? Days?
朋友们，我只是个临时容器而已 用来承载生命无穷的智慧
Friends, I am but a transitory vessel for the infinite wisdom of a creature
这智慧远比我们可以理解的先进得多
far more advanced than we'll ever truly understand.
他在这个广阔未知的宇宙里 看到的 感受到的
What he sees, what he feels of this vast, unknown universe
是我们简单的头脑无法容纳的 哦 可以动身了
is beyond anything our simple brains can... Oh. You can go.
什么
What?
出发 它说你们可以出发了
Go. You can go. He says "go."
你应该开快点
You should speed up.
啊 为什么
What? Why?
凯蒂 快 开快点 快
Katy, go, go, go!
莫里斯说 -三秒钟后方向盘向右打死 -啥
Morris says, - "Hard right on three." - What?
二……哪里开始右转啊
Two... Hard right where?
现在
Now.
然后左转
And left.
这一切都是为了留在口袋里
It's all about staying in the pocket.
什么口袋 -我们现在就在这里面
- What pocket? - We're in it now.
要是我们没留在这里会怎样
What happens if we don't stay in the pocket?
那样森林就会吃了我们
The forest eats us.
吃了我们 什么意思
Eats us? What does that mean?
他说就是森林会吃了我们 左转
He says it eats us. Go left.
-小心后面 -待在口袋里
- Watch your back! - Stay in the pocket.
-还有多远？ -5米
- How close is it? - Five metres.
-呆在口袋里 -五米是多少尺
- Stay in the pocket. - What is that in feet?
太他妈近了
Really fricking close.
呆在口袋里
Stay in the pocket.
你能不能别再说待在口袋里了
Will you just stop saying, "Stay in the pocket"?
最后一次右转 马上就要结束了
One last right, then straight on to the end.
你最好快一点
You might wanna hurry up.
不然你以为我在逛街吗
What do you think I'm doing?
要来不及了
We're not gonna make it.
我马上回“家”见你 妈妈
I'm coming home, Mummy.
莫里斯说“大家干得漂亮”
Morris says, "Great job, everyone."
现在我们只要穿过瀑布 就到了
Now, all we have to do is go through that waterfall, and we're pretty much there.
妈的
Bloody hell.
这些鸟是着火了吧
I think those birds are on fire.
真的诶
Really? Oh.
莫里斯说这很正常
Morris says it's normal.
他们是他旧时的伙伴
They're old mates of his.
这马长的真别致
That's a weird horse.
它为什么看着我
What's it looking at me for?
大家好!
Hi there!
我是徐尚气
I am Xu Shang-Chi.
这是我的妹妹 徐夏灵
This is my sister, Xu Xialing.
我们是映丽的孩子
We're Ying Li's children.
这是我的朋友 凯蒂
This is my friend, Katy.
上车 哪来的回哪去
Get in your car and go home!
你误会了 请听我们说
Please. You don't understand.
唔喔
Whoa.
光伯
Guang Bo!
你这是在干什么
What are you doing?
放下你们的武器
Put down your weapons!
尚气
Shang-Chi.
夏灵
Xialing.
我是你的小姨 映南
I'm your aunty Nan.
终于见到你了
I've waited so long to meet you.
像你妈妈
You look like your mother.
你好 我是凯蒂
Hi, I'm Katy.
欢迎来到塔罗 凯蒂
Welcome to Ta Lo, Katy.
谢谢
Oh, thank you.
看看谁回来了
Look who has found his way home!
我人畜无害
I'm not a threat.
就是个杂耍的
Just an entertainer.
莫里斯可以替我担保
Morris can vouch for me.
我们没有多少时间了
We don't have much time.
父亲就要来了
Our father is coming.
我们已经在这待了四千年
Our people have been here for over 4,000 years,
来准备应对一些我们永远不希望发生的事
preparing for something we hope will never happen.
我们是黑暗之门的守卫者 誓死保卫这片土地
We are the keepers of the Dark Gate, sworn to protect this realm
和你们的家园不受到困在门后的恶魔的伤害
and yours from the evil that's locked behind it.
我们的父亲就是来打开那扇门的
Our dad is coming here to open that gate.
他认为你把我们的妈妈关在那里
He thinks you're holding our mom there.
他怎么会这么想
Why would he think that?
妈妈告诉他的
She told him.
他说他能听到妈妈在向他求救
He says he can hear her asking for help.
他一直带着十环吗
Is he wearing the rings?
自从妈妈时候 他从来没有取下来过
He hasn't taken them off since she died.
十环和这一切有什么关系
What do they have to do with all this?
塔罗的领土一直延伸到我们小村庄的海岸线之外
The realm of Ta Lo stretches far beyond the shores of our small village.
我们的城市胜过你们宇宙中的任何一座城市
We have cities that surpass any in your universe,
孕育着非常丰富的文化和历史
rich with culture and history.
几千年前 所有族人都过着和平繁荣的日子
Thousands of years ago, all of our people lived in peace and prosperity,
直到遭受黑暗居民的袭击
until the attack of the Dweller-in-Darkness.
他带领他们的军队 吞噬了他们沿途经过的每一个灵魂
He came with his army, devouring every soul in their path,
每一次杀戮都使他们更为强大
and with each kill, they grew stronger.
在摧毁了我们最大的城市之后
After decimating our largest cities,
他们又进军到你们的宇宙再次进行屠杀
they were headed to your universe to do the same.
塔罗的领袖派出了最强大的一批战士
The leaders of Ta Lo sent their strongest warriors here
去阻止他们到达通往你们世界的传送门
to stop them from reaching the portal to your world.
但我们的祖先不是他们的对手
But our ancestors were no match for them.
直到伟大的守护者加入了这场战争 并扭转了局势
Until The Great Protector joined their fight and turned the tide.
他们共同奋力将黑暗居民军队
Together, they pushed the Dweller and his army
打进了黑暗之门 并且将他们锁在了里面
into the Dark Gate and locked it behind them.
从那之后 我们的族人就一直守卫着这道门
Our people have guarded that gate ever since,
守护者的魔力赋予了我们力量
empowered by the magic of The Great Protector
以及她送给我们的礼物
and the gift that she gave us.
龙鳞
Dragon scales.
能过做出上好的盔甲
Makes very good armour.
在你父亲之前有很多人来到这 想要打开黑暗之门
Your father isn't the first to come here to open the Dark Gate.
几个世纪以来 这些人不断尝试又不断失败
Many have tried and failed over the centuries,
他们都有一个共同点
and they all had one thing in common.
他们都被另一个世界的某种声音吸引着
They were lured here by the voice of something on the other side.
一种承诺满足他们最强欲望的声音
A voice that promised them their greatest desires.
所以你认为是噬魂者在和我们的父亲交谈？
So you think soul eaters are talking to our dad?
他们知道十环有能力让他们重获自由
They know The Ten Rings have the power to break them free.
喔
Oh.
给你
Here you go.
喔
Oh.
去射箭场
To the range.
什么?好吧
What? Okay.
呃 看来我要送些龙箭过去了
Um, looks like I'm gonna go deliver some dragon arrows.
你要送这些龙箭过去？
Oh, you're gonna deliver some dragon arrows?
嗯 我也得干点事
Yeah. Make myself useful, you know.
谢谢
Thank you.
去看看你母亲吧
Let's go see your mother.
好羡慕你们知道自己想要做什么
I just love how you guys know exactly what you wanna do,
然后用一生的时间来精通它
and you spend your whole life getting really good at it.
我希望也能和你们一样
I wish I was more like that.
但是好像每次我稍微擅长一些事情
It's like every time I get moderately good at something,
我就会半途而废 然后尝试新事物
I just quit and start something new.
我知道自己的极限 所以我不会浪费时间
But I just know my own limits, and I'm not gonna waste my time
去追求一些最终会让我失望的事情
chasing something that will ultimately be a disappointment for me.
那不是我
That's not me.
光伯
Guang Bo.
让她试试
Let her shoot.
如果你心中没有靶子 就是无的放矢
If you aim at nothing, you hit nothing.
你们曾经是她的一切
You were everything to her.
她知道你们总有一天会到这里来找她
She knew that one day you would find your way here
所以她让我为你们的到来做了准备
and asked me to prepare something for your arrival.
失去了这么好的她之后 时常觉得活着很孤独
After losing someone like her, it's easy to feel alone in this world.
但你们没有
But you're not.
你们是这个家的孩子 我欢迎你们回家
You are children of this family, and I welcome you home.
这里不是你父亲的家
You're not in your father's house any more.
在塔罗 每个人都可以练武
In Ta Lo, we train as equals.
是时候从影子里走出来了 孩子
You've been in the shadows long enough, my child.
广波，你看到了吗
Guang Bo, you saw that?
我射得相当不错吧
That was tight!
我母亲是唯一一个可以打败我父亲的人
My mother was the only one who could beat him.
告诉我她是如何做到的
Show me how she did it.
停一下
No, sorry.
抱歉 越位了 越位了
Sorry. Offside, offside.
你妈妈知道她自己是谁
Your mother knew who she was.
你知道自己是谁吗
Do you?
你是所有前人的延续
You are a product of all who came before you.
你是家族的遗产，无论好的坏的
The legacy of your family, the good and the bad
都是构成你的一部分
it is all a part of who you are.
别再逃避了 外甥
Stop hiding, nephew.
这样只会让你沉湎于痛苦
It only prolongs the pain.
我们很快就能团聚了
We'll be together soon.
先生
Sir.
人手准备好了
The men are ready.
通道将在黎明时打开
The passage will open at dawn.
我会准备好车
I'll prepare the vehicles.
以心行气
Lead with your breath.
以气运身 要先掌握阴阳的转换
Look into your heart, the light and the dark.
你才能找到内心的平衡 从而真正认识自己
To know yourself, you must face them both.
你丈夫想灭了我们
Your husband tried to destroy us.
我们今天是来回礼的
The Iron Gang is here to repay that debt.
他已经不是以前的那个人了
My husband is not the man he used to be.
那我不管
It doesn't matter.
你们之间的事情跟我的孩子们无关
Your business with him has nothing to do with my children.
放了他们可以 但这个礼 必须得有人来接吧
They can go, but someone has to pay.
灵灵 尚气
Xialing. Shang-Chi.
进屋去
Go inside.
我跟客人有话要说
I'm going to talk to our guests.
可你现在没有魔法了呀
But you don't have your powers.
尚气 别怕
Shang-Chi, you have nothing to fear.
妈妈
Mama.
爸爸
Papa.
她说我是可以改变的
She told me I could change.
我也可以放下以前
That I could leave my past behind.
可是她错了
But she was wrong.
如果我当初没有把它们摘下来
If I hadn't taken them off,
那些混蛋根本就不敢动手
those men wouldn't have dared to do this.
我要它们付出代价
And now they will pay for it.
你的老板呢
Where's your boss?
我不知道
I don't know!
我真的不知道
I swear I don't!
那好
Okay.
血债必须要血偿
A blood debt has to be paid by blood.
你愿意帮爸爸吗
Will you help me?
我们找到害死你母亲的人了
We found the man responsible for killing your mother.
你有权为我们两个人了结这件事
It is your right to finish this for both of us.
你回来以后
And when you return,
它们会像以前一样对十环卑躬屈膝
we will rebuild The Ten Rings to what it once was.
我到处找你
Been looking everywhere for ya.
你没事吧
You okay?
我和你所想象的不一样
I'm not who you think I am.
你已经道过歉了 我不是在说那个
You already apologised for that. We're good... That's not what I'm talking about.
好吧
Okay.
你…想说什么
What... What is it?
当时我爸爸让我去找杀害我妈妈的人
When my dad sent me to find the man who killed my mom...
我之前说我下不了手
I told you I couldn't go through with it.
我撒谎了
I lied.
我以为我可以改名
I thought that I could change my name,
然后开始新的生活 假装那些事都没发生过
start a new life, pretend like it never happened.
但…
But...
她一定会讨厌现在的我
She would hate the person I've become.
你七岁的时候 你爸就开始训练你成为一名杀手
Your dad trained you to be an assassin when you were seven.
你14岁的时候 他就让你去杀人
He sent you on a hit at 14.
你也知道这很荒谬 对吧
You realise how messed up that is, right?
我妈妈被害死时 都是因为他
My mom is dead because of him.
现在他还要毁了她的家乡
And now he's coming to destroy her home.
血债必须要血偿
A blood debt has to be paid by blood.
你在说什么
What are you saying?
我要用他教我的本领
I'm gonna do what he trained me to do.
亲手杀了他
I'm gonna kill him.
他来了
He's here.
不行
No!
你还没准备好
You're not ready.
她留下
She stays here.
你居然要帮监禁你母亲的人
Are you here to help the people holding your own mother captive?
她没有回来
She isn't back there.
那个怪物在骗你 它想毁灭我们所有人
You're being lied to by a creature who wants to destroy us all.
他是这么跟你说的吗
Is that what they told you?
我清楚我妻子的声音
I know my wife's voice.
她是我姐姐 我和你一样想念她
I miss my sister as much as you do,
但绝不是用这种方式来纪念她
but this is not the way to honour her memory.
你们纪念她的方式 就是把她关在那扇门后面吗
Did you honour her when you turned her away from your gate?
混账 我们拒绝的人是你
You fool. We turned you away.
你过去造的孽 会毁了这个地方
The sins of your past would have destroyed this place.
小子 跟我讲话礼貌点
Be careful how you speak to me, young man.
我吃的盐比你吃的饭还要多
I've lived ten of your lifetimes.
让我过去
Let me pass.
不行
We cannot do that.
把这儿烧了
Burn it down.
拦住他!
Stop him!
你打算仅凭一己之力阻止我？
Are you planning to stop me all by yourself?
我不怕你
I'm not afraid of you.
不 你怕得很
Yes, you are.
你这一生都在恐惧中度过
You've spent your entire life afraid.
抱头逃窜 东躲西藏
Always running, always hiding.
他们找上她的时候 你就在旁边 但你什么都没做
You were there when they came for her, and you did nothing.
光站在窗边 眼睁睁看着她死去
You stood at a window and watched her die!
妈妈不在了 我们需要你
She was gone and we needed you.
但是你眼里只有那破十环
But you chose those damn rings over us.
把自己的儿子训练成了杀手
You trained your son to be a killer.
这满意了吗
Is this what you wanted?
就算你能带她回来
Even if you could bring her back,
你凭什么觉得 她还愿意和你扯上关系
what makes you think she'd want anything to do with you?
来救我
Save me.
快来救我
Save me, my dear.
救我
Save me.
我们回家了
I'm coming, my love.
他在破坏门
He breached the gate!
不合作的话 我们都会命丧噬魂怪之手
Those things are gonna kill us all if we don't work together.
你难道觉得我对付不了这玩意儿？
You think I'm going to fall for that?
你们的武器对付不了他们
Your weapons are useless against them.
我们不需要你们的帮助
We don't need your help.
我们可是无所不能的十环帮 才不需要
We are the mighty Ten Rings, and any...
我们…我们还是合作吧
We... We should work together.
放了他们
Release them.
都解开
Release them!
他们在做什么
What are they doing?
把吸取的灵魂带回给门后还没出来的家伙
Stealing souls to feed the Dweller-in-Darkness.
等他积攒够了力量 就会直接冲破大门
If it grows strong enough, it will break right through the gate.
那还只是开始
That was just the beginning.
太危险了
It's too dangerous.
我要帮我的朋友
I have to help my friends.
活着回来
Don't die.
所有人马上到湖边集合 快
Everyone to the water now!
到湖边 快走
To the lake! Let's go!
快走!
Let's go!
嘿，你哥哥在哪
Hey, where's your brother?
我还指望你知道
I was hoping you knew.
救我
Save me.
齐天共战 视死如归
Aim at the sky, to win or die!
深吸一口气
Deep breath.
尚气 别怕
Shang-Chi, you have nothing to fear.
你有神龙之心
You have the heart of our dragon.
你是妈妈的血脉 也是爸爸的
I will always be a part of you. And your dad will too.
你要把我们给你的一切化成你自己的力量
Take everything we've given you and make it your own.
你是妈妈的骄傲
I'm so proud of you.
我们家需要你
Our family needs you.
去吧
Go.
开弓
Draw.
放箭
Fire!
你得阻止你父亲
You have to stop your father!
她不在这里 爸爸
She's not back there, Dad.
别碍事 孩子
Get out of my way, boy.
不
No.
哥们 冷静
Calm down, mate.
我没死 是装的
I'm not dead, it's just a performance.
配合一下
Now get down here and play along.
我必须救她
I have to save her.
她在呼唤我
She's calling to me.
我也希望这是真的
I wish that were true.
爸爸 求求你
Dad, please.
你的家人都需要你
Your family needs you.
放我出去
Let me out!
该死
Shit.
它朝着村子去了
It's headed for the village!
如果神龙的灵魂被吞掉了 就什么都阻止不了它了
If it gets our dragon's soul, it will be unstoppable!
对准它的喉咙
Aim for the throat!
放手吧
You have to let me go.
放手
Let go!
我不会再离开你了
I'm not leaving you again.
天呐
Holy shit.
去吧
Go.
今晚 我们缅怀那些为了我们而牺牲自己的人们
Tonight, we honour those who gave their lives so we might see another day.
他们不仅是战士
They were more than warriors.
他们也曾为人父母 是我们的兄弟姐妹
They were our mothers and fathers, our sisters and brothers.
我们会永远记得他们
And though we will always hold on to their memories,
今晚 他们要和祖先重聚了
tonight we release them to rest with our ancestors.
爸 走好
Farewell, Dad.
妈妈 放心吧
Mum, we'll be okay.
千年以前直到千年后的现在 他们永远都在一起
A thousand years ago, and a thousand years from now, we will always be together.
我真的以为我们会死
I seriously thought we were going to die.
我才刚学会射箭不到一天 现在我和尚恩的小姨一起
And I'd only learned how to shoot a bow, like, a day earlier, now I'm on a battlefield,
在战场上杀吸灵魂的怪物 尚恩的小姨简直就是神奇的功夫女神
killing all these Soul Suckers with Shaun's aunty, who's this awesome, magical kung fu goddess.
我当时正在跟守护者和我妹妹一起
And I'm hanging on to The Great Protector with my sister at this point,
奋力抵抗巨大的吞噬者
trying not to get eaten by the Mega Soul Sucker.
那玩意儿真不是个东西
Oh, the Mega Soul Sucker was such a nasty bitch.
就是 它还想吸了我们神龙的魂
Yeah. It was trying to eat our dragon's soul.
一旦被它吸走 得到的力量就足以毁灭整个世界
Which would have allowed it to destroy the entire universe.
是的
Yeah.
我当时只剩一支箭了 我听到脑海里我妈妈的声音响起
I only had one arrow left, and all I could hear in the back of my mind was
“给我一箭射中 妈妈的小机灵鬼”
my mom's voice saying, "Just take the shot, you little mooch!"
我就直接瞄准噬魂者的喉咙
And so, I aimed right for the Sucker's throat
-让龙箭飞 -她真的一箭中的
- and I let her fly. - She hit it dead on.
接着尚恩用十环搞出一个像龟派气功一样的大火球
And then Shaun used the Ten Rings to do this crazy Kamehameha fireball
把那玩意儿炸了 于是他就拯救了世界
that exploded the thing... ...and he saved the world.
诶 好多人牺牲了
Yeah, we, uh, lost some good people that day...
但我们做到了
but we made it.
没错 我们做到了
We made it.
你们有完没完 还要嘲讽我们到什么时候
Are you done mocking me?
啊 没有啊 我们可没嘲讽你
Oh, no. We're not mocking you.
所以 你那个妹妹哪去了
So where is this sister of yours?
她回我爸爸的帮派了 她要彻底解散那里
She's back at my dad's compound, shutting down his operations.
是啊 他爸爸是存在了几千年的十环帮的首领
Yeah, his dad was the head of The Ten Rings for the past thousand years.
两周之前 你们还在靠泊车赚小费
Two weeks ago, you were parking cars for tips,
现在你想让我相信 你打败了噬魂者
and you want me to believe you're now saving the world from soul-sucking monsters?
我懂了 你们是想为上回的事找借口
I know, you're trying to get me back for what I said last time,
但我并不打算道歉 因为我拿你们当朋友才会这么说的
but I'm not gonna apologise... ...for speaking the truth as a friend.
我说真的 甚至觉得你们说的更加佐证了我的看法
I really meant what I said, and, in fact, I actually think this whole bit you're doing just further proves my point.
你们俩显然是…-干嘛 -尚气
You guys are obviously... - What? - Shang-Chi.
尚气
Shang-Chi.
这儿
Uh... Here.
到
Present.
我是王
My name is Wong.
我知道 先生 我是你铁杆粉丝… 你真的拥有十环吗
Yeah, I know, sir. I'm a huge fan... Do you have the rings?
嗯 对啊
Uh... Yeah, yes.
好 跟我走 我跟你还有很多话要说
Good. Let's go, we have a lot to talk about.
还有你
You too.
还有我的份？
Me too?
-我觉得咱们应该… -哦 对 没错
- I think we should... - Yeah.
-我们得走了 -是的
- Uh, we gotta go. - Yeah.
我知道这很难接受，之后跟你发短信解释
I know this is, like, crazy, but I'm gonna text you,
如果有机会的话 很高兴见到你 约翰
and we'll do this again. Nice to see you, John.
我会跟你们平摊账单的
I'll Venmo you for the...
独立日你开着敞篷车兜风
You was crusin' with your top down Fourth of July
我开着车 我们在红绿灯前停下
I was movin' down the block We got caught at the light
我想追求你
Out my window I was shooting my shot
看着天上的烟火
Watching fireworks in the sky
就是你了 就是你了
I'm calling it now I'm calling it now
我爱上了你
I'm calling it now
你会爱上我
You'll find love with me somehow
就是你了
Yes, somehow I'm calling it now
夏天我们开着敞篷车 享受阳光
In the summers we let the top down Soak up the light
我只想锁定我今生所爱
All I wanted was just to lock down the love of my life
像午夜兜风一样简单美好
Nice and simple like a midnight drive
看着天上的烟火
Watching fireworks in the sky
就是你了 就是你了
I'm calling it now I'm calling it now
我爱上了你
I'm calling it now
你会爱上我
You'll find love with me somehow
就是你了
Yes, somehow I'm calling it now
喔 喔 喔
Ooh, ooh, ooh
描绘你的每词每句
Every line, every word every noun and verb can define you
喔 喔 喔
Ooh, ooh, ooh
你很害羞但让我停车
You were shy but you told me to pull over
我在你身后
And now I'm right behind you
我们进展很快 但感觉很对
We was movin' kinda fast but the feeling was right
今晚就去内华达结婚
We should cruise up to Nevada Get married tonight
只要你在 生活就简单
Life is simple as long as you're in my life
看着天上的烟火
Watching fireworks in the sky
就是你了 就是你了
I'm calling it now I'm calling it now
我爱上了你
I'm calling it now
你也会爱上我
You'll find love with me somehow
对 就是你了
Yes, somehow I'm calling it now
嗯。
Hmm.
典籍里没有这样东西
They don't match any artefacts from our codex.
你怎么看
What do you think?
嗯 我不确定
Mm, I'm not sure.
不是振金 也许是齐塔瑞人的
They're not vibranium. Chitauri?
我没见过这样的外星技术
Not like any alien tech I've seen.
在交给你之前 你爸拥有十环多久了
How long did your dad have them before he gave them to you?
呃…一千年吧
Um... About a thousand years.
根据热释光来看 十环的年龄不止一千年
Their thermoluminescence indicates they're older than that.
远超一千年
By a lot.
你第一次使用十环的时候 我们在卡玛泰姬就感觉到了
The first time you used the rings, we felt it in Kamar-Taj.
感觉到了什么
What is it?
一个信号
A beacon.
他们在发送信息
They're sending a message.
发给谁
A message to where?
不好意思 我有事要去处理
I'm so sorry. I have to deal with this.
布鲁斯有我的电话号码
You can get my number from Bruce.
很高兴见到你
It was so nice to meet you.
…我没有她的电话号码
Yeah, I... I don't have her number.
…她经常这样
She... She does this a lot.
注意安全
Guys, stay safe.
欢迎加入
Welcome to the circus.
要理解和吸收的东西很多 但你得慢慢习惯
I know this is a lot to take in, but you're gonna have to start getting used to that.
你们的人生轨道 已经彻底改变了
From now on, the trajectory of your lives will be like nothing you've ever experienced before.
而且没有回头路
And there's no going back.
前路漫漫
You both have a long journey ahead of you.
回家好好休息
Go home, get some rest.
好主意
Yeah. That's a good idea.
对 该好好休息了
Yeah. Yeah, we probably should do that.
或者…
Or...
欢迎来到加州旅馆
Welcome to the Hotel California
多么美丽的地方 多么美丽的地方
Such a lovely place   Such a lovely place
多么可爱的脸庞 多么可爱的脸庞
Such a lovely face   Such a lovely face
加州旅馆有很多房间
Plenty of room at the Hotel California
-无论何时 -无论何时
Any time of year   Any time of year
都可以来住
You can find it here
她爱慕虚荣
Her mind is Tiffany twisted
开着奔驰
She got the Mercedes bends, uh
有一群帅气的朋友
She got a lot of pretty, pretty boys she calls friends
他们在庭院跳舞 留着香汗
How they dance in the courtyard, sweet summer sweat
有的想铭记 有的想忘却
Some dance to remember, some dance to forget
我叫领班送点酒
So I called up the Captain "Please bring me my wine"
他说从1969年起就没有了
He said, "We haven't had that spirit here since 1969"
那些声音仍在召唤
And still those voices are calling from far away
在深夜里叫醒你
Wake you up in the middle of the night
听他们说
Just to hear them say
欢迎来到加州旅馆
Welcome to the Hotel California
多么美丽的地方 多么美丽的地方
Such a lovely place   Such a lovely place
多么可爱的脸庞
Such a lovely face
他们在加州旅馆纵情狂欢
They livin' it up at the Hotel California
-多么美妙的惊喜 -多么美妙的惊喜
What a nice surprise   What a nice surprise
准备好借口
Bring your alibis
他们在等着了
They're waiting.
开始吧
Let's get started.
我们有很多事要做
We have a lot of work to do.